knowledge is power reality
[Music]
a little bit more about your audience
and how this I can make a great
experience for them right right so
um
I would say I do I do speak to like the
leader side in all of us fairly often
the podcast kind of started as a mental
health podcast I'm just talking about
like depression and our inner experience
and what you can do to make it better
sort of thing a lot of people sharing
their personal experience
um and so I think the audience is
probably
people looking for like those little
golden nuggets of advice to to make
their life a little bit better than it
is you know so also if that helps yeah
yeah that helps wonderful all right well
ladies and gentlemen welcome to the
junkyard love podcast I am here with
nikkier anani uh it's it's so great to
have you on today
um I've got got a little bit of notes
here but like I said we'll just kind of
keep it casual and uh and see where it
falls in so I would love to start
um with your bio with your background
what it is that you do
awesome thank you thank you for having
me Jacob I'm excited about our very
organic conversation
um I in a nutshell help business owners
build Legacy Enterprises so move from
Lifetime businesses to Legacy and who am
I I'm a second generation business owner
myself
um I'm based in Austin Texas very
recently moved here from Lagos Nigeria
about six weeks ago and my journey into
helping folks in Legacy planning was
very much intertwined with my life
Journey
so my father started off uh business day
I was born
and this was back in late Boston Nigeria
and at age nine myself my mum and my
brothers we moved to the UK so I was far
from the business for many years
and I went to University in London I
worked in corporate in Deloitte for a
few years but I found it so dull it
didn't inspire me
and I felt a bit lost as well
so I decided to take some time off and
travel
and my first stop was to go to Nigeria
to work with my dad just for a few
months
and so all the time myself and my my
brothers my mum were in the UK he stayed
back and was building out the business
so by the time I came back from my short
stint I was only supposed to be back for
three months the business had completely
changed from when I was a child
um it was now a construction company a
real estate development company and an
engineering company
and there were now 3 000 members of
staff
and but there was very informal
so it was a huge culture shock from
coming from London from nice and tidy to
Lloyd's and yeah the cultural change the
industry changed and everything
and but I it was what lit me up so it
was contrast from my experience in
Beloit because like I said I was
thoroughly bored but here everything was
on fire like the entrepreneurship
opportunities and Lagos
um I just really loved it that there was
such a huge opportunity to add
tremendous value to customers and wider
stakeholders communities
whilst uplifting focus on that Journey
um through the trickle-down economic
effect right
um and so it's quite a long story short
I didn't leave I stayed past my three
months I was there for 10 years actually
and but I found that there was very
little help out there to help navigating
with integrating into a family
Enterprise
there was very little help out there
with helping to build a legacy business
and but I thought that it was really
important that businesses like my dads
shouldn't just die when he dies but
unfortunately
the data in Nigeria was that only two
percent of businesses would outlive
Founders like my father
and so essentially I got trained up with
family farm Institute in Boston to
become a certified family business
advisor and that started my journey
um with first putting in the governor's
succession planning with our family
Enterprise to see that it would outlive
um Dad and hopefully even my generation
and then helping other folks to do the
same so that's that's how I got here wow
yeah yeah what a journey I was thinking
about um I feel like many people might I
mean 3 000 people is a big deal of
course but I think many people may even
Overlook that intuition to you know
because you decided I'm gonna travel for
a while I don't know exactly what I'm
gonna do and you don't know exactly what
you're looking for in the first spot you
go you go back and just to to make the
decision to say okay I think actually
this is what I'm supposed to be doing I
think a lot of people might Overlook
that you know maybe they might keep keep
searching maybe they need a couple more
years travel a couple more places so I
mean it's pretty powerful and awesome
really that you were able to to grab
hold of that when you went back on your
first place
I must say it was a gradual process so
it was so the plan when I was in London
before I came to Nigeria was I've been
in Lagos for three months I'll go
traveling in the Far East for six months
and I'll go to business school
um the following September
at the end of the three months I was
like
I don't want to go let me extend it for
another three
and then at the end of those three it
was like I don't want to go let me
extend it for another year because I was
still I was on a career break with
Deloitte at this point so I've been
given one year
um off work
and I extended that to two years and at
the end of the two years I was like I'm
not going anywhere this is where I'm
supposed to be
um the it was just on fire I just I I
got I love the entrepreneur's life
yeah the fact that you're just creating
things that other people need
it wasn't really so much about money but
really that value creation that I just
really loved
and also like I said in unfortunately in
Nigeria we are the poverty capital of
the world and so in this process of
economic value creation you are
adding tremendous economic value to
folks that really do need jobs
we do need opportunities so that really
um I really enjoyed that so yeah it
wasn't
it wasn't as soon as I got to Nature I
was like yes I'm going to be here for 10
years it was really like you know what
let me just see where this takes me and
see
whether this is where I feel I was
supposed to be at this point in time
yeah yeah take it step by step I I like
that
um just thinking about okay so when you
got there we have three three thousand
people and um it sounds like it was
unorganized a bit or or maybe just just
not prepared for that amount of people
that much scale I'm sure so what are the
things
I'm sure you learned a ton
um but what what are some of the things
that you learned that that you were able
to take back and say all right here's
what we got to do different here's where
we need these people here's where we
need these people because I'm sure you
kind of like were a total Maestro coming
back in after going and and taking that
class learning about what you need to be
doing coming back in and implementing it
and what were some of the major changes
that that you found yourself having to
make or Implement it's organization yeah
um the importance of HR
um as not just an administrative
function not just paying salaries and
making sure that people are granting
leave right but really being as a
strategic function so aligning that with
the Top Line where's the Saw heading
like the culture we want to build the
vision the mission
um and then cascading that all through
the organization
um having Clarity of the goals of the
company and being able to translate that
to departments and then to individuals
then we had
a huge issue with ghost workers when I
moved back so we're a construction
company we had 110 projects across the
country
and it was largely manual so the only
software people were using was literally
like Excel Microsoft Word and emails so
yeah there's a lot of leakage
so looking at just putting in controls
so I brought an internal order
um biometric
um time and attendance verifications
um doing lots of kind of spot checks of
the the
salaries that were being paid to whom a
lot of the time found that these people
didn't exist or they'd left the firm
years back it was just it was a horrible
experience yeah it was a horrible
experience
um
and then also delineating
functions and roles
a lot of the time someone would be like
yes I'm a procurement officer that's
what I was hired for but actually I'm
doing admin work
I need to find there was a lot of
duplication in that regard so there's
lots of inefficiency so
doing job description audits
um okay this is what you were hired for
what are you actually doing
um do we need to update your JD
do we actually then need you in this
department do you need to be moved
somewhere else to he needs you for stop
in the company so there's a lot of
tedious work in that regard a lot of
people management and also on H um also
on finance
right
she was also largely informal
um and then how does that how does that
map over to kind of like the work that
you find yourself doing with with other
companies like where where they're
hiring you to come in do you find a lot
of the kind of similar things where
maybe businesses grew too quickly or
they you know they just didn't put the
the correct Scaffolding in place or
precisely a lot of business businesses
grew too quickly
and the router centers around an
individual
and so it's very
[Music]
um
founder Centric
and instead of building an institution
where so typically you'll see that the
founders surrounded by helpers
you do this you do that okay
I've done it
just task
clusters as opposed to code builders
um and so yeah I always say that if
you're trying to build a legacy
Enterprise
um it if it's going to outlive the
founder the founder has to be able to
spend a week or two away from the
business and the business can function
without him or her right if we can't do
that then we can't even talk about
generational
um and so the very first step is
business foundations
HR Finance standard operating procedures
processes procedures all that yeah right
right yeah so
so yeah a large part of your work is is
obviously helping with
um
intergenerational uh business yeah so so
what does that look like I mean do you
have
do you find yourself working with a lot
of you know father-son sort of
situations or you know a few few tears
down
um is a lot of their issues kind of just
typical father-son not getting alongside
type stuff or or what do you see often
there
I've seen father son mother daughter
cross gender sometimes siblings teams
with fathers yeah
um a lot of the time the conflict arises
because the founder
is finding it really difficult to let go
so they've been the one that built this
business from inception right and they
see it they want to retire but in
reality they're hugging it and stifling
this business and no one else can get a
word in
and that's the really the Crux of the
matter and that's what's causing a lot
of conflict
and that's when I'm pulled into the room
right okay we want to succession plan
but how do we actually go about doing
this or there's a lot of sibling rivalry
you know
um in that regard
or the of the unfortunate has happened
the founder that has passed away and
it's like okay what do we actually need
to do yeah yeah what steps we need to
take
um unfortunately we don't want that
situation where it's in crisis when
we're planning
it makes it a lot more difficult
um ideally you want to plan
early as yesterday yesterday is always
you know ideal it's never too early to
start planning Legacy planning because
it takes time it takes time for the
family to come together and start having
a Cadence of conversations on
where's this going
right what's that purpose
how do we fit into this I think that's
probably questions that you probably
proposed to to companies and they might
be the first time they've really thought
about it like what are our values where
are we where are we you know steering
this ship what do we want in 10 years
what's our scalable goals or or whatever
you know and that's something that even
in all of our personal lives you know is
helpful helpful to do as I'm learning as
I'm getting older just stumbling into
walls and whatnot figuring it out I'm
I'm more and more in favor of having a
what am I aiming at you know I think
that would actually be helpful
yeah I think we've all been conditioned
to do
just keep doing things right right it's
supposed to be
and to actually take a step back and
have full clarity as to what is the
purpose of this and you know this is
Jacob has is able to articulate his
vision his values his purpose
but you've also got other folks in this
process as well right
um so
how do you then Galvanize a team your
family members
so also crew
who create the vision the mission the
purpose and the values so often folks
haven't
given sufficient thought to this because
they're seemingly more pressing urgent
matters to deal with making money in the
business making daily decisions working
in the business but we have to make the
time to work on the business
um and in a family business that entails
creating
emotional room
um a time a Cadence
for challenging conversations
unfortunately
because it's not something that it's
just right you've got four options which
one do you like red pink blue would you
like meat or fish no it's not it really
takes deep introspection
um it takes
consider conversation
to collectively arrive at that point
yeah yeah and those are you know those
are difficult questions to ask yeah and
they're they're certainly not like a
check the box and and we'll choose which
one those are in in-depth long
conversations you know looking at the
future of you know everyone involved
personally and financially and uh what
the overall goals are are going to be
um so what do you
uh when it comes to leadership
what what
how about this how do you define
leadership
[Music]
um
I often say though excuse me leader
comes from an Old English word which is
go before as a guide
um so as a leader
you facilitate you inspire you motivate
you've gone before everyone else around
you have an idea of vision where we're
heading
and you're just influencing and
motivating rallying people along on the
journey to come with you
um it's not rulership
it's not power over
it's not domineering
it's inspiring
I liked it that's a fantastic definition
for leadership so do you find different
leadership styles in um you know I think
of just our older generations and then
you know just the younger Generations
Millennials gen Z whatever just because
technology has changed what we do how we
do it why we do it it's just changed so
much it's really taken over
um a lot of what we do and I feel like
it brings out different different ideas
in us as Leaders you know um I I imagine
there's probably just a big disconnect
in the types of leadership in the places
we want to take things older Generations
versus versus the young
um do you find
excuse me do you find that um
that like technology and maybe taking
risks or um uh getting away from you
know because at some point when you have
a business it works it works great to
have you know handshakes and emails and
just Microsoft Excel and and whatnot but
and then you at some point you gotta
build a website and it's gotta work well
and then you got to have social media
and so I imagine there's probably a lot
of
um resistance to that sort of growth do
you do you find
um a lot of that sort of thing
for sure I think typically you'll find
that the older generation will focus on
this is how what we did to get to where
we are so why should we have to do
things any differently
whereas the Next Generation younger
folks are more Future Folk as well this
is the way the future looks like it's
going towards and we need to catch up
otherwise we're going to be irrelevant
and that can create this Chasm between
the generations where it's there's a
resistance to change and there's a
hunger for change on the other side and
it's to bridge that process
um we we do need the resiliency of the
all but we also need the novel of the
new
and
back to your point on um leadership I
think and heck I think Tech has kind of
it's it's Rewritten the game like all
the rules of the game right because
a lot of the older folks ruled by
position
through their titles and their Authority
and
there was a lot of information and
symmetry right with the focus on the
field and those up in the boardroom
but now
from our fingertips it's like no
this we've got the data and we're
empowered and we've got you know we're
leaders in our own right and so there's
also been like a cultural shift away
from that positional
um to really more the younger generation
wants to be inspired they don't want to
be
um told what to do they want to really
connect with why
the true purpose
um and there's huge kind of skepticism
and yeah there's a lot of um what's the
word
skepticism and what's the word I'm
looking for just suspicion suspicion
okay yeah we're a very suspicious
Generation
Um Millennials we don't like us t-shirts
right
um and so we don't want you to tell us
what to do show us why we have to do it
show us the bigger picture I'm sure how
it's adding value
um the authentic so these are all the
kind of
generational gaps we typically see is in
the style of leadership
um which is apparent in family firms as
well this can really hinder
collaboration
um because
both Generations are just talking over
each other it's like they're speaking
different languages
and unable to come together and truly
collaborate and that's a lot of the work
that I do is to bridge that Gap
yeah yeah definitely
um just sidestepping really really quick
I'm actually in Austin Texas Texas as
well um I'm going to move out here like
four months ago yeah so I was just
curious what brings you what brings you
out to Austin oh that's so cool um
foreign
yeah like in January we're like we're
done we need to move so we decided
in in April we came myself and my
husband came out to check it out like
um because we decided on Austin without
ever visiting Austin yeah
I'm making this International moves a
bit a bit of a gamble um so we decided
let's actually check it out first
and we love that yeah and by may he was
here and July myself and the kids came
yeah that's so awesome yeah it's a it's
been similar similar for me um just kind
of needed some change a lot of
difference happens and so so I'm out
here I feel like there's a lot of people
I mean of course there is a lot of
people that moved to Austin you know
from from really from everywhere
um and I'm I'm really interested to see
what it does to to like the culture you
know it's gonna be really cool you know
the next the next 10 years like
everybody coming here with with their
ideas and their individual perception
and how they see it you know like so so
what do you see I'm sure that you're
probably naturally you probably watched
you know business Trends and like
cultural Trends and kind of where things
might be going do you think about the
future of places like Austin with a
bunch of people moving here oh for sure
I'm
super passionate about
cognitive diversity right
and the way we think which is shaped by
our life experiences who we are and
things and I strongly believe that more
diverse teams
well not just the existence of the
diversity but truly in true inclusion
leads to co-creation of better Solutions
because of the different kind of World
Views that we're all coming with and
we've got
um Western culture which is very
individualistic promoting you know
pursuit of Independence and
um whereas in other cultures you've got
collectivist cultures like in Africa
Middle East and
Asia which is more collectivist and
really
um more about the community more about
upholding one's honor reputation so I
think
there's Confluence and this kind of
melting pot of different people with
different experiences and different
ideas might bring about better social
Solutions
as well as stronger business ideas as
well so I think it's exciting I think
from everything I've experienced so far
super inclusive yeah yeah
um and it's really up and coming it's
like this Melting Pot of everyone is
here yeah it feels like that for real
yeah and I think we're gonna see really
cool ideas come out in business sphere
as well as in Social
space as well yeah yeah I I think so too
um obviously of course you have your
your finger on the pulse closer than I
do but just as kind of a a Creator and
someone who enjoys culture and um just
as as like my
my view as as an artist or whatever I'll
call myself
um I I'm just I'm so like wow this is
going to be really cool I'm very excited
you know um and I'm I think uh it's cool
you know we have people people like
Tesla or Elon Musk moving out here with
Tesla and I think HP moved out here you
know Joe Rogan moved out here and he's
bringing all these comedians so that I
mean if you have a bunch of comedians
coming into a town you're definitely
gonna have the culture changed you know
um yeah so I I'm just really really it's
very exciting and I'm happy to be here
and welcome I'm glad you're here too
thank you
um so the so do you have any um any any
companies or any of like the big popular
people maybe maybe Tesla that people
look up to what what are some good
aspiring
um companies that have good cultures
that we might be able to point at and
learn from
that's a really good question
um
I would say Tesla's a great one Amazon's
a great one
um these are companies that encourage in
Innovation creative thinking allow for
fail fail fail fast
fail as fast as possible so you can get
back up because
not only do we have to allow for
diversity of thought
or diverse teams rather both in families
and in business
we also actually have to ensure that
these fruits that are diverse actually
have a voice we we listen and encourage
them to speak which is inclusion
um so having their voice heard at the
table but not only it's not enough just
to have their voice heard at the table
we want everyone to be empowered to be
agents to challenge the status quo let's
be able to be like hey Jacob I'm not
sure that's a good idea because this
might not work or we've done this and
it's failing we need to try something
new because it's it's in that place that
we see true creativity and unlock
innovation
looking at the macro we're going to see
it's been disruptive it's going to get
even more disruptive
um
a rate of technological innovation is
exponential and will continue to be so
so we cannot be static we have to be
dynamic we have to
um not just
um adapt to the times we have to create
the future and that can only happen if
we're creating cultures where
challenging is the norm
yeah yeah I like that that that's I mean
I completely agree I think that's that's
what it is I mean if you can create this
business to be an organism that is you
know self-correcting like on all of its
different aspects all of its nodes you
know your employees are are your
different edges of of it and when they
see something that maybe you can't see
because you're working on your you know
your area
um yeah it's worth it's worth listening
yeah I don't think I don't think having
a dictator at the top saying yes or no
all the time is is incredibly help
helpful I think that age is gone
um and we have to normalize
everyone must feel safe to make a
mistake
yeah because
it's
we have to normalize risk taking to some
extent right the safety
um that even I'm gonna try something new
if it doesn't work it's fine I learned
something from it
as opposed to
um I have to
stay safe and just to the line of best
fits
so I fit in and I don't stand now
that is not going to unlock Innovation
and creativity
um okay so do you see I I think uh I
mean I'm not in it
um I I like so I don't see I kind of see
more of like the news articles and what
you hear here and there but um you know
with our with our our interesting
culture right now
um inclusivity is so important and it is
great but I do see a lot of like over
correction of it of it um I see a lot of
uh
we're like mimicking we're like doing
like the mime version of it we're doing
the acting version of it making sure
everybody knows that that we're
inclusive instead of actually actually
doing it do you find a lot of that yes
it's exhausting it's a lot of eye
service it's like a PR campaign virtue
signaling of sense yeah yeah so it's
making me crazy yeah no it's it's BS
that's not what that's not inclusivity
right it's not about
festivals and women's day and those
things are great
um but it's really about
creating cultures that really make room
for people that look different and are
different yeah where everyone can say I
belong here my ideas belong here my
mistakes belong here yeah and everyone
can take not only kind of legal
ownership I'm an employee or but also
emotional ownership like
um I truly belong and I I truly desire
for the best for this organization and
so I pour my best into the organization
and organization reciprocates right yeah
like that's the identity we should be
meeting at like our community identity
like that's what we where we should act
from we meet each other on these
incorrect levels and then think we need
to react and respond to them and it's
like I don't care about that we're just
yeah we're here to create a community
and build a business together let's talk
about that and I think also
foreign
I have very strong views on this
um I think also we rob people of their
individuality because then it's like oh
all women this is the issues women face
or black people these are the issues
black people face at all
um you know lgbtq people this and we're
all individual there's a lot of nuance
right um I've had a number of people ask
me oh okay
um critical race Theory what you think
of ABCD I'm like I'm six weeks into
being in the US my lived experience
it's very different from an
African-American they have the same hair
we have the same skin color but my lived
experience is very different I cannot
tell you that
um we have the same life experiences and
I've had people of Caribbean origin say
the same thing
um where it's like
that's not necessarily the same for us
like there's some some similarities but
there's also some new odds and I think
it's the same for any groups of people
there's
they're all individual yeah and we just
want our individuality to be recognized
and we don't want to be ashamed
belittled the denied access because of
whoever we are right let's just make
room for
people's differences
um
be curious about people's differences
rather than judge them I think there's a
judging that happens when we just put
people into categories and just assume
um their issues
and without really being curious to
learn about each individual yeah yeah I
mean because I I find that I mean
through my lived experience through my
in conversations when you don't meet
people on on the level of like you know
what the news is telling us we should
look at this part of their identity you
know it's just just be with them and
talk with them and you'll find that you
know you're probably going to get along
with them with them just fine I think
the you know technology in in news and
social media and a lot of this it kind
of takes us out of our definitely takes
us out of our present you know we're
we're kind of living up up in our minds
in these like
um stories that are written about
stories that are told you know and and
they're saying this is this is what it
actually is so we're kind of fighting
this this Phantom sometimes in in a way
you know and and I think that getting
present and just you know dealing with
with who you're dealing with in our
everyday life is is kind of more the way
to go in my opinion
yeah
um so yeah it's a and it's it's also
interesting to note that uh this area of
conversation is like an eggshell area in
in a sense like we're not allowed to to
talk about it uh I I did a did a couple
episodes on cancel culture actually with
a friend of mine um who's just a an
armchair philosopher and we're kind of
just like like what is this why are we
paying so much attention to this you
know and this I think we really do need
to just get back to back in in our heads
in our bodies and just deal with what's
in front of us
absolutely agree I I did want to thank
you for your for your opinions on that
too um Nikki um so I did want to I was
thinking about first generation
businesses so
people who are starting to get some
growth they're they're the ones with the
idea they're the founders they're
getting employees things are growing
maybe they have a couple stores maybe
they have a couple locations
um you know at what point should we
start thinking about
tightening up like all right let's
actually get our get our 10-year plan
you know what what do we need to be to
be thinking I actually have one friend
in particular who um he's a clothing
company
um I feel he's going to be very
successful he already has multiple
Stores
um he started out I used to he used to
sell t-shirts out of his trunk at
parties that I would DJ you know he's
got multiple stores and he's just a
really cool guy um but he has he has a
child on the way if if not already has a
child and so I imagine in a few years
he's going to start thinking like all
right what do I want to do with this
business and and how do I want to expand
and how do I want to you know teach my
kid about it or bring my kid into it I'm
not sure so just kind of what's on my
head so um tell me about first
generational business what's our mindset
here I think with first genres
um I always say there's a distinction
between
um maturity and age right just as we all
know some old folk are not mature
um there's no correlation often it's the
same with businesses they're quite often
you have a business might be in a
startup phase where you're trying to
prove the concepts and get it to
commerciality
at
pre-pre it's been able to stand on its
own two feet and generate consistent
revenue on profits that's a a business
that's really in baby mode and I
wouldn't invest a lot of time thinking
doing deep planning at that stage
however once the business has crossed
that threshold you need to be planning
yesterday
um so just as in construction because I
have a construction background you you
start with the end in mind you have your
architectural drawings you have your
engineering plans you need to know
because you need to know that the
load-bearing capacity of the foundations
depending on the height of building and
the materials that you're going to use
and the design of the house is similar
right so ideally we want to start your
legacy planning
um as soon as the business demonstrate
that it's viable
and
that doesn't necessarily mean that you
have all the details and you know what
role Johnny is going to play in 30 years
time in the business it's probably
impossible right
um but it is really gaining Clarity on
like what we were talking about earlier
Clarity of Mission Vision and conviction
and starting to have expose your
children to the business
um they might not be the leaders of the
business but they will probably be the
owners of the business in the future and
that comes with responsibility
and as owners we don't want them to be
just legal owners without emotional
ownership we really want them to care
about the business and that's only going
to happen when they've you don't fall in
love with what you don't know
um so you wanna for as early as possible
just talk about the business take them
to the office and that doesn't
necessarily mean you impose it upon them
and demand that they take over but you
just naturally show them expose them and
they may become curious they may be okay
Dad I want to spend more time I want an
intern
um I'd like to study something along
this line at College I'd like to plug
into networks and then you know that
okay this one has a flair for the
business whereas another child might be
like
this is boring boring yeah what role are
we playing in the community how can we
help folks that are less you know not as
well as well off as us and then you know
this this child has a flair for like
philanthropy or Community CSR and things
like that so oh you might have a child
that's like we need to think about life
insurance we need to think about
structuring uh assets we need to think
about other Investments
and then you know okay this one seems to
be very good with diversification but
guess what we need
the confidence of all three skills right
to build a business of the future
um because it's it's really thinking
through the technical structuring as
well as leading the business as well as
okay what other assets
do we have as a family and how can we
protect the family so yeah I would say
start with the end of Mind start to
create a Cadence for these conversations
with family with your spouse if possible
um with your kids
um from an early age to really and also
expose them from an early age because
Legacy is long term it takes time
it's not something you figure out in 90
days
um and it takes intentionality it takes
intentionality it takes time for your
kids to develop their leadership
and I mean that mean that in a broad
sense right I don't mean whether they're
going to lead the business I mean even
as a philanthropist you're a leader even
as an investor you're a leader it takes
time for them to develop that and it
takes time for them to develop
to become Visionaries
it's like we said as a leader you're
going before as a guide so you have a
picture of what this is about you're not
just tactical you're not just functional
you're not just you know a door
um it takes time for them to develop
that and then it also takes time for
them to come together
and practice leading together because
the business will grow from lead being
led by
Dad or Mom
so in the Next Generation being
collectively led by
three four step lengths
taking joint ownership decisions are we
going to sell the business or where are
we expanding into a strategic
um advisors potentially as board members
and things so there's many moving parts
that we have to start thinking about
yeah yeah of course
so okay so how about how about let's do
second and third generation then
um so so people who
um in in that I also think about
um
new ideas uh maybe side steps pivoting
um that that sort of thing because I
imagine that could be you know that
could be a wonderful thing that could
all that could probably also be the
death of a company you know uh if it's
not planned out uh adequately or if the
side step or pivot is too far away from
the from the original
um
thing that the business set out set out
to do so yeah let's talk about second
and third generation how do we think
differently there
it's pretty similar but it gets more
complex because now you're moving from
siblings to cousins
all right and who've not grown up in the
same household
right and
um at least for siblings we all were led
by mum and dad who knew what they all
stood for we've probably involved
similar cultures to some extent there'll
still be variations right but now with
cousins sometimes you've never met them
they're halfway across the world across
the country have completely different
views
um and so it becomes even more important
to focus on that
team formation that Clarity of visual
Mission and conviction because guess
what that's a dynamic concept it's not
something that all Henry VIII decided
and yeah
1466 that this it has to evolve with the
times and with the stakeholders
um so we have to start thinking about
family learning
being intentional about family Retreat
spending time together being intentional
about
um yeah collectively ideating on this
visual Mission
um conviction and we have to be we have
to start running the family almost like
a company we have to create governance
committees
[Music]
um decision-making processes to minimize
conflict
yeah yeah okay well how do you think of
uh you've used the word legacy a couple
times and I think I actually I heard you
mentioned in another podcast I was
listening to as well
um and I I think I remember you having a
good explanation around it so how do you
think of the word legacy
hmm
I think of it as something that outlives
you so it's sowing a seed today
and you might not necessarily get the
immediate returns in that the fruit of
that seed won't Bud immediately
um the totality of that fruit well
um but immediately but it's going to
create a tree with so many fruits for
future generations to benefit from
that's Legacy
um there's a quote and I forget who said
it it's Legacy it's not giving someone
something it's giving people the ability
it's a skill which I love because back
to your point on like pivoting and
Reinventing so so apt
um all the studies on family and during
family businesses and Enterprises are
those where every generation bring
something new certainly they either go
into a new market or new product new
service new investment YouTube Adventure
and so
the Legacy really is not just
cash in the bank or
the manufacturing plan is really the
imbibing of that entrepreneurial skill
and when I say entrepreneurial skill I
I'm not just talking to those
next-geners or the rising generation I
have an inclination for entrepreneurship
because I believe the mindset of
Entrepreneurship is so so powerful and
it permeates through different aspects
of life so even the philanthropist needs
an entrepreneurial mindset the investor
the impact person the social person the
employee
um being an entrepreneurship's ability
to create something that adds value to
people and being able to make it
sustainable right from money perspective
so
so so yeah um
I think it's really really important
that we do
Legacy is not just about what people are
going to inherit
it's also the skills that they're
learning which is why learning is so
important for business families learning
together
learning individually learning
um the stories of the you know the
origins of the business and the business
founder
but also learning about the failures
um yeah I think even even having uh just
a growth mindset when it comes to
learning uh is just as an individual is
helpful to the overall business I mean I
I again I listen to you on some podcasts
and you mentioned brene Brown you
mentioned Simon sinek I love both of
them
um and so it sounds like you you are
constantly learning you're constantly
absorbing and feeding your mind this
this new knowledge and it makes you
better at what you do so you can help
more people right
um so what are how about some uh uh you
know little self-development tips what
are some ways that you you stay sharp
like do you do you make sure you're like
I'm gonna listen to this many podcasts a
week or are you just kind of casual
about it or um because we all we all got
to be feeding our our inner leader right
no that's a really good point so I kind
of have Cadence for learning oops
apparently
um and for me podcasts I just I love
them because that's just so convenient
right I can be doing the most mundane
thing but I'm learning at the same time
in a very
I find it entertaining way
um so I could be at the gym running and
time just goes like this because I'm
listening to friends educate me in my
ear
um so whenever I'm at the gym I listen
to a podcast
whenever I'm driving or in the shower or
doing any kind of interesting housework
I'm listening to something and I try to
make sure they range from mindset type
work emotional intelligence
entrepreneurship it's kind of societal
cultural it's just good
a total kind of view because I think
as business owners we need to work not
only on mindset which is foundational
um
being able to have a growth mindset
being able to be curious
um being able to
to take risk pursue possibility these
are are really critical as business
owners but we also have to be
strategists it's not not just great to
have yeah right yeah I can take all the
risks in the world but you've got no
clue how to go about doing so and you
don't know how to read Trends and see
the future so
um we also have to mind strategy and
then execution
being able to create accountability
structures to bring those files so aside
from like learning through podcasts I
read I really read when I'm on vacation
um I'll probably be through like four or
five books
um and and then I highlight them and
then read the notes like throughout the
year so
just I'll go back to random books I'm
like oh I'm a bit Rusty what what was
that book about and I just go through
only the highlights because I read on my
Kindle
and the most
impactful but unspoken about learning
for me is through connections
yeah through communities
um I'm in communities with other next
genres
industry groups
um impact philanthropy
um attention friends just conversations
like this right you
you
and with mentors as well mentors are
just like oh my god
um I'm really big on mentorship
because you're just you're infusing
Jacob's life journey by being open and
talking you're learning from his
mistakes and from his triumphs
right and vice versa and you developing
your Social Capital as well because
in being vulnerable like okay this is a
struggle area for me it's like well I've
got someone that you should really talk
to who might be able to help you with
that or can connect you to someone else
um so
being generous with your expertise
generous with your networks folks
reciprocate that and it's such it's such
a blessing
um so that's been a real way for me to
to really learn and develop this
connections I'm huge on
connections I spend a lot of time
building connections nurturing
connections and not in a transactional
way not just jump on a zoom and be like
right well yeah so here's my book buy my
book or let me get something from you
let me get something from you like I've
got coaching program do you have any
clients but really being in service
people just
just catching up sometimes they may be
going through grief and just being there
just
um
just being there for them and
and yeah just continue to develop that
relationship over time yeah yeah no that
that's great I mean really the you know
the the a lot of the core concept of of
my podcast at the junkyard podcast is
kind of you know
somebody needs something that you have
you know like some somebody like there's
somebody who's listening and if they're
really listening it can hit them right
in the right way right at the right time
and it's kind of like a in a junkyard
you know maybe a 1984 Buick LeSabre
front fender is not very beneficial to a
lot of people but to someone who has a
vehicle saber and they need a front
fender it's this is the exact piece they
need so just kind of like you know
really opening up to every conversation
you have every interaction you have it's
like what's what's the world trying to
teach me what's this person have have to
teach me you know and what can I teach
them maybe maybe I can teach them some
of my expertise and then that in turn
teaches me something about myself you
know so it's a yeah being being open to
in reciprocating to all this is I
completely agree and and the weird thing
is is that often you don't know the
total impacts you're making on Forex
lives
you don't know when you're you you're
giving someone the thing that you have
right and I think the same also holds
for legacy right
there's there's Generations I will never
meet and I don't know how I would have
impacts with them right yeah so just
always just be in a place of service and
forget about all those we all have those
niggling thoughts about how you're not
good enough you don't know anything and
you're a failure forget about those
people like the more you talk over them
they just they quieten down I rarely
hear them these days like there's some
days I wake up and I'm like yeah boy
you're a bit loud today I need to do
some mind makeovers
um but those thoughts are um Irrelevant
in the grand scheme of things in terms
of the impact you're making on people in
your generation and in generations to
come oh yeah beautifully said you know
in you know just that I've covered a lot
of uh the mental health area
um on the podcast and that is something
that I've talked about before is you
know hey that voice that that inner
nihilist you know we all we all have it
sometimes sometimes sometimes many of us
have it a lot more whatever whatever but
if you can kind of just you know stand
up to it and say ah no no thank you like
oh or or even oh okay so you're mad you
know oh I see you I see I see you mind
you know you're trying to be negative
about this thing but instead you don't
believe in yourself and focus on your
ideas and focus on you know what you
want to accomplish and and what you're
capable of doing and what you're capable
of bringing to to the world you know
it's it's super important I love that
you mentioned that like that that little
nihilistic voice I always love
mentioning that that Jekyll and Hyde
version of ourselves
yes
um so we are getting up here in time
um I do want to do so so typically I try
to find one last hard-hitting question a
lot of times
um I would ask you know what does the
world need more of right now
um but for you I think I want to frame
that uh if you're willing to answer uh
how about
what what's something that that the
leader in each of us could could use to
hear right now what's something that I
could speak to the leader in all of us
foreign
by possibility
and not caged by fear
okay I like that there's a lot more
possibility out there and there are
negative outcomes
um but those voices will amplify
the what could go wrong how it could go
wrong but
push past those if you can
and be powered by possibility because
there's just an infinite amount of
possibilities that the world has to
offer you and you have to offer the
world
[Music]
uh Valley I love that powered by
possibility not caged by fear That's So
Dope I love that um okay well uh let's
make sure we give the audience uh your
your website where can they find you
they can find you on Instagram and
Twitter and where are you at yeah my
website is first name last name.com so
www.nika n-i-k-e anani a-n-a-n-i.com
and I'm on Twitter Instagram Facebook
LinkedIn just at Nikka and Annie
everywhere
awesome cool well I will include that in
the description notes
um and everybody everybody go check her
out give her a follow on Instagram she
retweets some good stuff I was on her
Twitter earlier
um so definitely give her a follow Nikki
I really appreciate your time here thank
you so much for offering your your mind
to the listeners and and your time to to
me and and allowing me to ramble along
and formulate questions as we go it's
been a great ramble and it's been great
introspection learnings and Reflections
thank you so much for having me yeah
yeah fantastic well I mean again welcome
to Austin I know I'm kind of thank you
myself but welcome I hope you enjoy it
uh maybe get yourself some breakfast
tacos or something this weekend yeah
for sure well thanks so much again I'll
see you later listeners take care of
yourself love yourself do not be caged
by fear let's go
each doing that have better
conversations
at what age do we learn to have better
conversations with ourselves
[Music]
knowledge is power reality
is
[Music]